The basis of collectivity, the foundation
of collectivity, is very deep.
And the deep understanding can only tell you
that the basis of collectivity
is detached love.
Love is the only way.
It's not possible to have collectivity
unless and until you have detached love.
French have been good at so many types of
love that they have been talking about.
And they have written books after books,
novels after novels, and have created
lots of romantic and unromantic and
all kinds of atmospheres to talk of love.
But the pure love,
as we understand in Sahaja Yoga,
is to be now expressed by Sahaja Yogis among themselves.
After all, we are all human beings
made by one God.
And that we are all Sahaja Yogis
created by one mother.
So, there should be no misunderstanding
between us of any kind.
But we must know what sometimes
makes us little different.
If we can understand the problems that we
face, then it would be much easier
for us to see why our love becomes so attached
and not so detached.
Starts becoming smaller and smaller.
Then a person just starts loving oneself only.
One of the main reasons that we have this
problem is because of our conditionings.
We are conditioned the way that
we don't know how to love.
When I see the advertisements
in the West.
I don't know from where the
West starts and
where it ends, and
from where the East ends.
They talk of West and East, but I don't
know which is the demarcating line.
Can anybody tell me that?
Where do we start, East and West?
Because it's one round world, you see.
But somehow or other there is some line,
unknown line, underlying line,
which creates sometimes this East and West, two types of conditionings.
So when I see some advertisements,
they show about —
recently I saw about James Bond,
that he is free to kill and the best film for revenge.
This is the advertisement.
If revenge is the best way of fulfillment,
then how can we love someone?
So this kind of conditioning comes to us from outside,
that we should not forgive anyone.
We should take the revenge.
And, if you do not take the revenge,
then you are not worthy your name.
So if you cannot take the revenge
like a duel that they used to have in France
quite a lot between the two persons.
They would take two guns and kill each other.
I mean what a stupid idea it was. Just think of it in modern times.
But it was so.
So if the revenge is not
taken,
then it was thought to be something very sly, very low level.
So a person must take revenge.
History shows also the same things, that
one had to take a revenge of
another person who has harmed you; in any way troubled you.
I think it's the quality of a snake, they
say, that if you step onto any snake,
it follows you all his life
to take the revenge.
The only thing that it does
all its life is
to run after that person who has, by mistake,
put the foot on its body.
In the same way, a human endeavour I have seen in so many novels is suggested
how a man gets after a person who has some way or other harmed.
If we go on like this,
there's no end to it.
Firstly, it is absolutely absurd.
For that I will give you
an example of Buddha.
Very much I have been impressed by the way he said once.
Somebody who insulted him and abused him and said all kinds of horrible words.
Then Buddha went to another village.
Now this fellow felt the remorse
and he went back,
went back and said, "Sir, I'm sorry, I've said these things to you.
I'm really very sorry."
He said, "What?"
"Well," he said, "Yesterday —."
He said, "Yesterday is finished now.
You are now with me today.
So why are you talking about yesterday?
It's finished."
So, with this kind of idea that somebody has
harmed us, somebody is horrid to us we linger on
in the past.
So, the wisdom of Sahaja Yoga is in understanding
the limitations up to which you can go to express your anger,
to express your revenge, so called,
on anyone whatsoever.
But the best thing would be to leave it to the Divine power,
because everything is done by Divine power.
We all exist inside the Divine power.